Hello everyone and welcome back
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we've got an
upper intermediate level
lesson for you all about money.
That's right, we are going to
talk about the stock market.
So a very interesting
topic, very current as
well because well throughout the world,
stock markets are not doing very well.
That's right and you may have seen on the
television a lot of information about this.
So today we're going
to hopefully explain
some of the things and phrases
and words that you've been hearing.
But first we've got a
couple of important
indicators, a couple of acronyms
actually that you're going to hear about.
So let's look at those in
today's vocabulary preview.
Very capillary preview.
Alright, so the first word that we have
on vocabulary preview is the Nasdaq.
Nasdaq.
N-A-S-D-A-Q, so this is basically
the American stock market.
Right, it's an acronym.
Now it's a really, really
long acronym so we're
not going to get into
it but it is basically
the American stock
market where all these
companies are trading stock,
publicly traded companies.
Right, so publicly
traded companies, you're
basically trading their
stocks through Nasdaq.
Right, and now the next one that we have is
an indicator that which tells us how well
some companies are some stock are
doing and that's the Dow Jones indicator.
Dow Jones indicator, so
maybe if the Dow Jones is really
low for something, we
think it's not doing so well.
Right.
It goes up.
Things are improving.
Right, so usually the Dow Jones has the,
it's based upon the 50 biggest companies in
the United States, the 50
biggest publicly traded companies.
Now you can divide
it into like industrial
companies or
pharmaceutical companies, etc.
, but in general that's the
indicator and how it works.
Great, so let's take
a listen to today's
dialogue and find out
how these words are used
in context and we've back in a
moment to talk about what's going on.
Sorry to bother you, sir,
but I have some bad news.
What is it?
Well, the stock market just took a huge
plunge and we've lost a lot of money.
What do you mean?
What happened?
There are many factors that weigh
in, but Nasdaq is down 200 points.
The Dow Jones indicator also suffered.
Our portfolio is worth half of
what it was worth one week ago.
How is this possible?
You are supposed to be talking to our stock
brokers and making sure that our securities
and investments are safe
and making a profitable return.
I know, sir, we didn't expect a bull market
to become a bear market all of a sudden.
On the other hand, you still have some high
yield trash bonds and government bonds that
will give us enough liquidity to cut our
losses and reinvest in emerging markets.
We could potentially make this tragedy work
for us and make us think outside the box.
Who would you have to do?
One other thing.
Don't tell the rest of the
stockholders about this.
If they find out, it's the
end of this company.
All right, we're back.
So a lot of interesting words there.
I think a lot of them
were very specific to
the stock market and very
maybe a little bit difficult.
So why don't we take a look at a
couple of those and language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
Okay, so this first word is a very
important word in banking and finance.
We talk about portfolios a lot.
So portfolio.
Right.
So basically a portfolio is the
variety of things that you own.
For example, in the
stock market, it could be
stocks, it could be
bonds, it could be mutual
funds, et cetera, or for example,
if you're a company, your
product portfolio could be all the
products that your company owns.
That's right.
Our portfolio is worth
half what it was a week ago.
And so this is, this is
a sentence that means
we've lost half of the
money we invested.
Right.
All of our investments are in a portfolio.
We talk about them
as a portfolio and when
we lose money, we mean our portfolio
is worth less now than it was before.
Exactly.
And we'll, moving on, he starts to talk
about the bull market and the bear market.
So what is, what is this all about?
Well, a bull is an animal with horns.
Right.
And a bear is another animal.
So we're not talking about animals here.
Right.
We're talking about
special finance phrases.
Right.
So the bull market would be, again,
talking about companies and trading.
It would be maybe a market
that's growing very rapidly.
That's very, very strong.
That's a bull market.
So people often talk about
China's bull market, right?
Right.
Oh, China continues to grow
and grow and grow and grow.
But a market that slows
down like the United
States last year would
be a bear market.
Right.
A bear, maybe it's sleeping,
it goes into hibernation.
That's a bear market.
So a slow market is not really growing.
Very good.
But talking about a portfolio
again, we might have stocks.
But in this case, the two people
are talking about their bonds.
Right.
So he says, you still have some high
yield to trash bonds and government bonds.
What's a high yield bond
and what's a trash bond?
Okay.
So when we think about the word
yield is how much it gives, right?
So how much we are getting from it.
So something that is high yield
means that you're getting a lot from it.
For example, this orange tree
yields 300 oranges per year.
Okay.
So how much we get from it?
Exactly.
So we're getting 300 oranges.
That's how much it's yielding.
And so basically that's what yield means.
So when we talk about
trash bonds, this on the other
hand, it's a word that's
maybe a little bit tricky.
So a bond is a promise that you get from
the seller that he's going to pay you back
the money that you give
him with interest, right?
But a trash bond is a very risky bond.
It means that the seller might
not pay you back because,
you know, he's still
trying to get all the money.
All right.
But a high yield trash bond means that you
might make a lot of money from this bond.
Unless, of course, it's
not very dependable.
Exactly.
So it's risky.
Of course, since it's
riskier, it has more yield.
Great.
So high yields trash bond.
And then what about this?
They will give us liquidity
to cut our losses, liquidity.
We hear all about liquidity and finance.
Exactly.
Maybe in your company,
the accountant will
talk about this and has basically
just to have money cash in hand.
So you have money to pay
things or to buy things, right?
Okay.
It's available.
Available, yeah.
Not with credit.
The opposite of credit.
Okay, liquidity.
And finally, instead,
what are we going to do?
Let's think outside the box.
We could reinvest in emerging markets.
And this is a very hot topic lately
talking about emerging markets.
So to emerge means
to come up right to rise.
Yeah.
It's come out.
So it's almost like new or growing markets.
So in this case, a market,
an emerging market
would be, for example,
the Southeast Asian market,
which is growing quickly or even,
you could say, West African market.
We're talking about places in
the world that aren't established.
They're not old and dependable.
They're new and exciting.
Right.
So they're coming up.
So that's an emerging market.
So a lot of very interesting words and
phrases they're very related to our topic.
And so why don't we move on now?
Let's take a look at two key
phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Is first phrase is
something we've heard a
lot about in the last
year or two with things
not going so well in
the world of finance?
The first one, here we
go, to cut our losses.
Okay.
So let's cut our losses.
So when you talk about
cutting your losses,
that means to try and stop
losing money somehow.
Maybe sell early.
That's right.
So in this case, we're losing money.
Let's stop now.
Let's stop everything.
Cut our losses.
That means cut them away.
Forget about them.
Okay.
And start again.
So we could say, my business is failing.
I'm going to cut my losses,
sell the business and start again.
Right.
That's exactly it.
So to cut your losses
means to stop doing
something, maybe sell
it and stop losing money.
Basically, you accept
the fact that you lost it.
You can't get it back.
Right.
But you start again.
So when they were
talking about investing in
emerging markets, he said,
well, maybe we could do this.
And that would force us
to think outside the box.
Okay, this is a great
phrase and you might hear
this in meetings a lot
or from your manager.
What's going on here
is these two people are
talking about how
they lost a lot of money.
The economy is bad and they've been doing
things in a normal way for a long time.
It's not working.
Let's think outside the box.
That means let's be creative.
Let's try and discover new ways of doing
things that will yield positive results.
That's right.
Very, very common
phrase, very widely used in
business or when
you're talking about ideas
is people tell you to think outside the box
to maybe break some of the rules, right?
Right.
Don't just think the
way that you always do.
Don't do the same thing over and over.
Do something new.
Be creative.
Come up with something great.
So that's thinking outside the box.
Right.
Very good.
So a lot of great phrases there.
I think we've learned quite a bit.
Why don't we listen
to the dialogue one last
time and we'll be
back to talk a little bit
more about this very interesting topic.
Sorry to bother you, sir,
but I have some bad news.
What is it?
Well, the stock market just took a huge
plunge and we've lost a lot of money.
What do you mean?
What happened?
There are many factors that weigh
in, but Nasdaq is down 200 points.
The Dow Jones indicator also suffered.
Our portfolio is worth half of
what it was worth one week ago.
How is this possible?
You are supposed to
be talking to our stock
brokers and making sure
that our securities and
investments are safe and
making a profitable return.
I know, sir, we didn't expect a bull market
to become a bear market all of a sudden.
On the other hand, you still have some high
yield trash bonds and government bonds that
will give us enough liquidity to cut our
losses and reinvest in emerging markets.
We could potentially make this tragedy work
for us and make us think outside the box.
Do what you have to do.
One other thing, don't tell the
rest of the stockholders about this.
If they find out it's the
end of this company.
So I remember being
a little kid and watching
TV with my parents,
and on the news, there
was always the business segment, and you'd
always hear that Nasdaq is down 10 points.
But now Jones industrial
today is down 10
points yesterday was up
to, that's an average of each.
Okay.
Yeah, it's very complicated,
especially if you
take a look also in the
newspapers sometimes,
it shows you different publicly traded
companies and it has a bunch of numbers.
It's a very interesting topic.
It's almost a science, I think.
Very much as science, and some people have
made a lot of money, playing this, always
they're playing the stock
market and trying to buy stocks in
their low, wait and sell their
high, sell them off and make tons.
Yeah, it's pretty much analyzing risk.
So making calculated
decisions, and that's
why they use all these
formulas and all these
different ratios and
ways to ponder how much
they should invest or
what would they gain.
So it's very, very interesting, many people
compare it to gambling, but this, it's kind
of like gambling, but not really
because you don't really depend on luck.
You kind of make calculated decisions.
And sometimes you're
trading for big, big
companies or even parts of big markets,
like parts of entire countries, yeah, so.
A lot of people, for
example, stock brokers will
invest a group of
workers, retirement funds.
They will take those
funds and be like, hey,
you're maybe getting
5% from the bank for
keeping your money
there, give me the money
and I'll give you 25%
yield on your investment.
So that's, and so
obviously they're playing
not only their reputation, but
also with other people's life savings.
And that's why a lot of people lost money
when two years ago, the bubble really burst
with a lot in a lot of
areas like real estate,
stock prices went
down, the United States
went into a recession, and all
these people's retirement funds.
Yes.
The savings, they lost it.
And so you got to be
careful with this kind of
stuff and do your
homework, but that's about it.
For us today, hope that
you've enjoyed this lesson.
If you have questions or comments, please
do visit us on our website EnglishPod.com.
All right.
We'll see everyone there.
Bye.